Most of us know
that movement and exercise
are good for our physical health,
and science is showing
that they're also good
for our mental health.
But did you know that exercising
with friends comes
with its own unexpected benefits?
If you're the type of person
who likes to go to the gym,
put on some headphones and
kind of focus on your own thing,
this idea might seem a bit strange.
What difference could exercising
with other people actually make?
I feel like it's just so nice
to have the support of your friends
and your team-mates and everything,
and just having people cheer you on.
Everybody cheers behind you
and gets behind you and goes,
"Come on, you can finish it!
Last 500m!" and you know,
you know you're going to make it.
Humans evolved
as a social species.
Being around our friends makes us
feel safer and less cautious.
And this can change
how our bodies respond to exercise.
Fatigue evolved to protect us
from overexertion and injury.
It works like a brake mechanism
that tells us when we need to stop,
but it also limits our endurance.
When our social environment tells us
we're safe and supported,
our bodies can ease
that protective break.
So, by making us feel less fatigued
and more energised,
exercising with family and friends,
or even just as part of a group,
can actually boost
our physical performance.
To show this, we ran an experiment
with 25 teenage rowers
here at the Fulham Reach Boat Club.
We asked them to row at a set pace
for as long as they could
in two different
social environments.
One was designed to make them feel
socially supported,
and the other was meant
to make them feel on their own.
We found that those who felt
supported got tired less quickly
and were able to row
for a longer amount of time.
You see everyone else
row next to you,
you can sort of just zone in
and realise that you're not
the only one,
and also you have each other
cheering you on, of course.
Whilst you're on your own,
it's just really miserable, I guess.
In the boat with other people,
there's a sense of camaraderie
which you don't have in the boat
by yourself.
But on top
of boosting our performance
and making our workouts feel
a bit easier,
there's another major benefit
to group exercise.
You kind of have
that social aspect,
so it kind of gives you
a mental health benefit
by coming out to the runs.
I think the social activity-
I mean, I've got so many friends now
because of it,
and I think
that's one of the big bonuses.
And do a run
and a coffee and cake afterwards.
So it's just... Yeah, it's great.
Scientific research
is beginning to show
that the more we exercise
with our friends,
the closer we feel to them.
Evolutionary anthropologists
call this social bonding.
This happens because our bodies
release chemical messengers called
endorphins and endocannabinoids
during exercise,
which make us feel happy
and content.
You might have heard people saying
they give us a runner's high.
This natural high can help us
be more positive and in tune
with the people we're exercising
with, and this helps us feel closer
and more connected to one another.
And it turns out
these social connections
don't just disappear after exercise.
We followed over 50 teams
of teenagers who took part
in a challenge which required them
to navigate
a difficult 50-mile course
over two days.
Teams who reported working together
and supporting one another said
they felt closer and more connected
when they finished.
What we found really interesting
was that these feelings
of social connection positively
impacted their mental wellbeing
a whole week after the event.
Again and again, studies have shown
that social relationships
are really important
for our overall health.
When we feel lonely,
we get more stressed,
and this fight or flight response
is our body's way
of protecting itself
from the dangers our ancestors faced
when they were alone.
But in the modern world,
this stress response
can be a bit counterproductive.
And when loneliness causes us
to feel chronically stressed,
it can be harmful
to our long-term health.
One study even found
that lacking social connection
can be as dangerous for our health
as smoking cigarettes.
So by exercising together,
we're helping to build
the social relationships we need
to live happy and healthy lives.
When I'm here,
I'm not stressed about exams.
I'm not stressed about, like,
all of the other things I have.
Like, it's just rowing
and I'm just here with my friends.
But what happens
if you don't have family and friends
nearby?
Maybe you've just moved,
or maybe you can be a bit shy
and you're not sure
where to meet people.
It turns out there are a lot
of exercise groups and clubs
that are happy to get new members,
even if you're just getting started.
In fact, some are even specifically
for beginners.
I found the group on Facebook,
and it was set up as an event,
so I just clicked "going".
I was really nervous about it,
going for the first time,
worried about meeting new people,
but they were so welcoming,
there wasn't really anything
to worry about, really.
And if you can't do
intense exercise,
finding a partner
to go on light walks with
can also have positive effects
on your health.
In fact, any kind of
physical activity that we can do
in collaboration with other people,
so things like dancing, gardening
or singing,
can help us move more
and feel more socially connected.
Public health experts have described
rising levels of physical inactivity
and loneliness as two new epidemics
that are harming our physical
and mental health.
It turns out that exercising
together,
or even just being active
with other people,
might help to cure both.